<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Danny James Williams</title>
    <link>https://dannyjameswilliams.co.uk/projects/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://dannyjameswilliams.co.uk/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://dannyjameswilliams.co.uk/images/icon_hu6de9a8f7dd4e8a8bd7c2613cf2ad59bf_37670_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://dannyjameswilliams.co.uk/projects/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gaussian Process Classification</title>
      <link>https://dannyjameswilliams.co.uk/projects/gpc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dannyjameswilliams.co.uk/projects/gpc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The second group project I worked on at COMPASS mainly involved learning how Gaussian process classification worked, as it is a complicated procedure, and not as straight forward as Gaussian process regression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our work involved a number of aspects that have improved on Gaussian process classification in recent literatures:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pseudo-Marginal Likelihood:&lt;/strong&gt; An importance sampling procedure to approximate the marginal likelihood in MCMC sampling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Subset Selection&lt;/strong&gt;: An entropy based measure that chooses a subset of a full dataset that maximises information across the dataset, referred to as the &lt;em&gt;Information Vector Machine (IVM)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laplace Approximation:&lt;/strong&gt; An approximation of the posterior of the latent variables.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together, these approximations makes Gaussian process classification feasibile. Without approximations such as these, the procedure would have an incredible runtime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we compared the results on an e-mail spam dataset, and had a higher prediction accuracy than a JAGS implementation of logistic regression. We combined our code, written in Rcpp, into an R package, available 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dannyjameswilliams/gpc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chicago Crime Classification</title>
      <link>https://dannyjameswilliams.co.uk/projects/chicago/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dannyjameswilliams.co.uk/projects/chicago/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My most recent project was a group project as part of the first term of the COMPASS CDT. It involved modelling different aspects of a large data set detailing crimes in Chicago. Pictured is a kernel density estimate of both the location of crimes in the city as well as the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My input to this project was to use logistic regression methods to classify whether an arrest would be successful or not, given other covariates in the crime set; detailing the location, the area, the type of crime type, amongst others. This involved feature engineering and using LASSO coefficient paths to judge the most &amp;lsquo;important&amp;rsquo; covariates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The package that was created for this project can be found as a Github repository 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jakespiteri/chicagocrime&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Downscaling Extremes of Precipitation in the South West</title>
      <link>https://dannyjameswilliams.co.uk/projects/precip/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dannyjameswilliams.co.uk/projects/precip/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For my Masters dissertation project, I used extreme value theory to model the extremes of precipitation across the South West of the UK, and downscale sparse areas using a numerical weather model on a gridded scale. Pictured is the high resolution elevation levels across the South West, with a grid that samples the same elevation levels every 0.25 degrees in longitude and latitude. This highlights one of the problems with downscaling in such a scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extreme values of rainfall can be categorised by their maxima, and using a generalised extreme value (GEV) distribution, these maxima can be modelled. I modelled two sets of maxima separately; for the observations (point locations) and the model output (gridded locations). A separate downscaling generalised additive model (GAM) was used to compare predictions from both models, and link them together using various covariates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read more about this project in my final dissertation, which can be found 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://dannyjameswilliams.co.uk/pdfs/proj/mastersdiss.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
